Guide to the Edmund Clarence Stedman Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series I: Correspondence, Manuscripts, and Diaries
  - Wood, Thomas Waterman (Box 176)
  - Wood, W.A. (Box 176)
  - Wood, Wallace (Box 176)
  - Woodberry, George E [n.d.] (Box 176)
  - Woodberry, George E (1883-1907 & n.d.) (Box 177)
  - Woodhouse, E.N. (Box 178)
  - Woods, Kate Tannatt (Box 178)
  - Woods, Matthew (Box 178)
  - Woodyear, Rosa B1anche (Box 178)
  - Woolf, Benjamin Edward (Box 178)
  - Woolfenden, Emma C (Box 178)
  - Woollett, Sidney (Box 178)
  - Woolsey, Theodore Dwight (Box 178)
  - Woolsey, Theodore Salisbury (Box 178)
  - Woolson, Abba. Louisa Goold (Box 178)
  - Woolson, Constance Fenimore (Box 178)
  - Wordin, Thomas Cook (Box 179)
  - Wormeley, Katharine Prescott (Box 179)
  - Worthington, John (Box 179)
  - Worthington, Mary (Box 179)
  - Wortman, Denis (Box 179)
  - Wray, W.A. (Box 180)
  - Wrenn, Johm H (Box 180)
  - Wright, Henrietta Christian (Box 180)
  - Wright, J.O. (Box 180)
  - Wright, John Dutton (Box 180)
  - Wright, Mabel Gray Osgood (Box 180)
  - Wyman, Melissa D (Box 180)
  - Yale, Leroy Milton (Box 180)
  - Yard, Robert Sterling (Box 180)
  - Yenowme, George H (Box 180)
  - Yownans, Kate L (Box 180)
  - Young, Arthur (Box 180)
  - Young, Charles Augustus (Box 180)
  - Young, Francis G (Box 180)
  - Young, James Carleton (Box 180)
  - Young, .James Walter (Box 180)
  - Young, William Wallace (Box 180)
  - Zerega, Katherine Barry di (Box 180)
  - E.C. Stedman’s diaries (Box 181)
- Series II: Uncataloged Correspondence
  - Copies, A-Z (4 Boxes) (Box 1-4)
  - Copies Stedman to A-Z (6 Boxes) (Box 5-10)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Manuscripts (Box 24)
- Series III: Letterbooks
  - 1864, 1884 (First Letterbook) (Box 11)
  - March 1876 -June 1877 (Box 11)
  - 1877, 1879 (Business) (Box 11)
  - 1879 (Stockbroker) (Box 11)
  - October 1881-March 1883 (A) (Box 12)
  - March 1883-October 1884 (B) (Box 12)
  - 1883 (Lib. Am. Lit. Matter) (Box 12)
  - October 1884-May 1886 (Box 12)
  - December 1884 -November 1888 (Lib. Am. Lit.) (Box 13)
  - January 1885-March 1887 (D) (Box 13)
  - May 1886-May 1888 (E) (Box 13)
  - August 1887-July 1889 (F) (Box 14)
  - 1889-1890 (Lib. Am. Lit [1]) (Box 14)
  - 1889, 1890 (Lib. Am. Lit II) (Box 14)
  - March 1889 -August 1892 (G) (Box 15)
  - July 1889 -November 1890 (H) (Box 15)
  - May 1890 -December 1891 (I) (Box 15)
  - January 1892 –January 1893 (J) (Box 16)
  - 1892, 1893 (Downtown) (Box 16)
  - January 1893 -February 1894 (Box 16)
  - February 1884 -April 1895 (Box 17)
  - April 1895-May 1896 (Box 17)
  - May 1895-October 1897 (Box 17)
  - May 1896-January 1898 (Box 18)
  - October 1897-May 1902 (Box 18)
  - January 1898 -January 1899 (Box 18)
  - January-July, 1899 (Box 19)
  - July 1899 -January 1900 (Box 19)
  - January-October, 1900 (Box 19)
  - October 1900-June 1901 (Box 20)
  - June 1901-January 1902 (Box 20)
  - January -August, 1902 (Uptown) (Box 20)
  - 1902, 1903 (I) (Box 21)
  - 1902-1903 (II) (Box 21)
  - 1902, 1907 (Downtown) (Box 21)
  - November l903 -December 1904 (Box 22)
  - 1903-1904 (Box 22)
  - 1904-1905 (Box 22)
  - 1905-1906 (Box 23)
  - March 1906-July 1907 (Box 23)
  - 1907, 1908 (Box 23)
  - Copies of poems and some letters, n.d. (Box 23)
  - Index (in 15 notebooks) Compiled by Laura Stedman Gould. (Box 23)
- Series IV: E.C. Stedman’s Writings
  - Aaron Burr's wooing (Box 25)
  - Abraham Lincoln (Box 25)
  - Ad Grahamum abeunttem (Box 25)
  - Ad sorores doctas (Box 25)
  - Aërial navigation (Box 25)
  - Alas, poor Yorick! [Eugene Field] (Box 25)
  - The album (Box 25)
  - [Aldrich, Thomas Bailey] (Box 25)
  - Alice Wellington Rollins (obituary) (Box 25)
  - An American anthology (Box 25)
  - Ariel (Box 25)
  - Astra coeli (Box 25)
  - Astraea (Box 25)
  - At the morgue (Box 25)
  - "Ave! Color vini clari (Box 25)
  - Bacchanal (Box 25)
  - The Bacon-Shakespeare case (Box 25)
  - The battle of Bull Run (Box 25)
  - Bayard Taylor (Box 25)
  - A belt of asteroids (Box 25)
  - Betrothed anew (Box 25)
  - Beyond the portals (Box 25)
  - Bill in favor of the Miss. & Mo. R.R. (Box 25)
  - Blanchette to Bronx (Box 25)
  - Bohemian days at Pfaff's (Box 25)
  - Brownstone utopia (Box 25)
  - Byron (Box 25)
  - Captain Francisca (Box 26)
  - Carmen. Innuptias felicissimas triumpale … (Box 26)
  - Castle Island Light (Box 26)
  - A catch (Box 26)
  - Centuria (Box 26)
  - The Century Club (New York) (Box 26)
  - Charles Henry Webb (Box 26)
  - Charley (Box 26)
  - Chastity (Box 26)
  - Chorus in Helen - Euripides (Box 26)
  - Christian and Christiana (Box 26)
  - Christmas: 1859 (Box 26)
  - Christmas in· the camps (Box 26)
  - Christophe (Box 26)
  - Church sparrows (Box 26)
  - Clara Morris (Box 26)
  - Clubs (Box 26)
  - Concerning Mr. Spofford’s plan for an academy (Box 26)
  - The constant heart (Box 26)
  - The copyright bill (Box 26)
  - Corda concordia (Box 26)
  - Country· sleighing in New England (Box 26)
  - Cousin Lucrece (Box 26)
  - Creole lover's song (Box 26)
  - A crisis in triolets (Box 26)
  - A critical estimate of Mrs. Stoddard's novels (Box 26)
  - Danäe and Perseus - Simonides (Box 26)
  - Dartmouth ode (Box 26)
  - The death of Bryant (Box 26)
  - The death of George Belmore (Box 26)
  - The diamond wedding (Box 26)
  - A dirge Smith E. Lane, Esq. (Box 26)
  - A distressing misquotation [letter to The Dial] (Box 26)
  - The doorstep (Box 26)
  - The Dutch patrol (Box 26)
  - Edwin Booth (Box 26)
  - 1865-1890 (Box 26)
  - Emerson (Box 26)
  - En attendant (Box 26)
  - England's poet-laureateship (Box 26)
  - Episode of Austaeus - Virgil: Georgic 4: 317-538 (Box 26)
  - Epitaph of Bion (Box 26)
  - "Ergo Iris" (Box 26)
  - An evening over poems (Box 26)
  - Eventide (Box 26)
  - Falstaff's song (Box 26)
  - The fate of a fowler (Box 26)
  - Father Jardine (Box 26)
  - Fern-land (Box 26)
  - Flood-tide (Box 26)
  - Forty years (Box 26)
  - The freshet (Box 26)
  - Gen. Halleck & Battle of Shiloh (Box 27)
  - Genius (Box 27)
  - Genius and other essays (Box 27)
  - George Arnold (Box 27)
  - George W. Smalley (Box 27)
  - Gettysburg (Box 27)
  - Gifford (Box 27)
  - Glimpses of heaven (Box 27)
  - Gold forgery, 1870 (Box 27)
  - Good-bye, Walt! .Walt Whitman. (Box 27)
  - Garaeco-English epigrams (Box 27)
  - Guests at Yule (Box 27)
  - H. van D. [Henry van Dyke] (Box 27)
  - The hand of Lincoln (Box 27)
  - Harebell (Box 27)
  - Hawthorne (Box 27)
  - The Hebrew pastorals (Box 27)
  - Heliotrope (Box 27)
  - Helen Keller (Box 27)
  - The hillside door (Box 27)
  - Holmes (Box 27)
  - Home (Box 27)
  - Homeward bound (Box 27)
  - Honest Abe of the west (Box 27)
  - The honeycomb-thief (Box 27)
  - Hope deferred maketh the heart sick (Box 27)
  - Horatius [to Austin Dobson] (Box 27)
  - The house that Vander built (Box 27)
  - Hovey, Richard (Box 27)
  - Howells, William Dean (Box 27)
  - Hymn of the west (Box 27)
  - It the earth were a cube (Box 28)
  - Immortality (Box 28)
  - In good old colony times (Box 28)
  - In memory of Charles Frederick Stedman (Box 28)
  - In Rose Hutchinson's album (Box 28)
  - The inland city (Box 28)
  - Intercollegiate literary contest (Box 28)
  - Introduction [to the Gustave Doré edition of Poe's The raven] (Box 28)
  - Introduction to "Vignettes in rhyms" by Austin Dobson (Box 28)
  - Introductory remarks at the Keats-Shelly Entertainment (Box 28)
  - Italy (Box 28)
  - J.C.R.D. [Julia C.R. Dorr] (Box 28)
  - J.G.H. (Box 28)
  - Jamaica (Box 28)
  - James Russell Lowell (Box 28)
  - Jean Pouvaire's song (Box 28)
  - Jean Valjean’s epitaph (Box 28)
  - John Godfrey Saxe (Box 28)
  - John Hay (Box 28)
  - John Morrisey (Box 28)
  - Le jour du rossignol (Box 28)
  - Juliet's runaway, once more (Box 28)
  - Katharine and Eugenio (Box 28)
  - Kearny at Seven Pines (Box 28)
  - Keats (Box 28)
  - Keats-Shelley Memorial (Box 28)
  - Kennst du? (Box 28)
  - King -"the frolic and the gentle" (Box 28)
  - Landor (Box 28)
  - "The last of the buffalo" [Albert Bierstadt’s painting] (Box 28)
  - The last token (Box 28)
  - Latter-day British poets (Box 28)
  - The lay of Harmodius (Box 28)
  - Letter from Edmund C. Stedman [re. the Boston Gazette] (Box 28)
  - Letters to journals (Box 28)
  - Library of American literature (Box 29)
  - Life "on the floor" (Box 29)
  - Lines written in the album of John Hay (Box 29)
  - Literary estimate and bibliography of Richard Malcolm Johnson (Box 29)
  - Longfellow (Box 29)
  - The Lord's Day gale (Box 29)
  - The Lord's Prayer (Box 29)
  - Lovers in the tropics (Box 29)
  - Madrigal (Box 29)
  - Map of Lake Winnipisseogee (Box 30)
  - Markham (Box 30)
  - Mater coronats (Box 30)
  - May: 1859 (Box 30)
  - Memoranda [on dreams] (Box 30)
  - Memorandum [on a projected literary magazine] (Box 30)
  - Memories of the Masonic Hall services. [O.B. Frothingham] (Box 30)
  - Menn (Box 30)
  - Meridian (Box 30)
  - Miss Field's debut [letter to The Tribune] (Box 30)
  - Mr Charles Henry Webb (Box 30)
  - Mr Howells and his friends (Box 30)
  - Mr Money Coutts's "Alhambra, etc." (Box 30)
  - Mr Stedman on the late Dr Powers (Box 30)
  - Mr Stoddard's seventieth birthday (Box 30)
  - Mrs Stoddard's novels (Box 30)
  - Monopolists as practical reformers (Box 30)
  - Montagu (Box 30)
  - The monument of Greeley (Box 30)
  - Mors benefica (Box 30)
  - A mother's picture (Box 30)
  - Musae Americanae (Box 30)
  - The music of the hoof (Box 30)
  - My brother's character (Box 30)
  - My godchild (Box 30)
  - The nature and elements of poetry (Box 30)
  - New England ballad (Box 31)
  - New England drama (Box 31)
  - New York (Box 31)
  - The New York Stock Exchange (Box 31)
  - New York University--Hall of Fame (Box 31)
  - News from Olympia (Box 31)
  - Night-mists (Box 32)
  - Notebooks (2) (Box 32)
  - The obligations of Tennyson to Theocritus (Box 32)
  - Ode for Commencement Day (Box 32)
  - Ode to pastoral romance (Box 32)
  - The old admiral (Box 32)
  - The old picture dealer (Box 32)
  - On a picture by McEntee (Box 32)
  - On every heighth there lies repose (Box 32)
  - On reading the foregoing song of degrees (Box 32)
  - On the death of an invincible soldier (Box 32)
  - [On the New Testament] (Box 32)
  - On the old dock (Box 32)
  - The opening of the Adirondak (Box 32)
  - Our juvenile poet has a mother… (Box 32)
  - Painting and poetry compared as means of expression (Box 33)
  - Panam (Box 33)
  - [Paper tax, 1863] (Box 33)
  - Perdita (Box 33)
  - Peter Stuyvesant's New Year's call (Box 33)
  - The pilgrims (Box 33)
  - Poe, Cooper, and the Hall of Fame (Box 33)
  - Poe's cottage at Fordham (Box 33)
  - Poems now first collected (Box 33)
  - Poems of occasion (Box 33)
  - Poetry in America (Box 33)
  - Poets of America (Box 33)
  - A poet's tribute to Lowell (Box 33)
  - Portrait d’une dame espagnola (Box 33)
  - Preface to "New England Society--Orations" (Box 33)
  - Preface to "The garden of years…" by Wetmore Carryl (Box 33)
  - Prelude (Box 33)
  - The prince of the power of the air (Box 33)
  - The prince’s ball (Box 33)
  - The protest of faith (Box 33)
  - Psi U Choral (Box 33)
  - Question d'argent (Box 33)
  - Recipes for punch (Box 33)
  - Reminiscences (Box 33)
  - A representative triad. Hood-Arnold-Proctor (Box 33)
  - Review of Bryant·"Odyssey" (Box 33)
  - Review of "Cathedral days" by Anna Bowman Dodd (Box 33)
  - Review of "Love-lore" by W.J. Linton (Box 33)
  - [Review of] Mr Stoddard's poems (Box 33)
  - [Review ot] Mrs Stoddard's poems (Box 33)
  - Review of "Tempest-tossed" by Theodore Tilton (Box 33)
  - Review of "The builders & other poems" by Henry van Dyle (Box 33)
  - Review of "The life of George Brummell… (Box 33)
  - Review of "The seven seas" by Rudyard Kipling (Box 33)
  - The rime of the Elle-King (Box 33)
  - Rip Van Winkle (Box 33)
  - Robes of honor (Box 33)
  - The rose (Box 33)
  - The rose and the jasmine (Box 33)
  - Rosemary (Box 33)
  - Round the old board (Box 33)
  - Sargasso weed (Box 34)
  - A sea change (Box 34)
  - "Sentiment" for Mrs Potter Palmer’s "Child’s book" (Box 34)
  - The Seventh (Box 34)
  - 70 degrees North (Box 34)
  - The singer (Box 34)
  - Sister Beatrice (Box 34)
  - The sleigh-ride (Box 34)
  - Some London poets (Box 34)
  - Song. The sunset… (Box 34)
  - Song. Thou art mine… (Box 34)
  - Song of the surf (Box 34)
  - The songster (Box 34)
  - La source (Box 34)
  - Speeches:
    - The Aldine Dinner for R.H. Stoddard, 1872 (Box 34)
    - Bayard Taylor funeral, 1879 (Box 34)
    - Bayard Taylor Memorial, Goethe Club, 1879 (Box 34)
    - Sidney Lanier Memorial, Johns Hopkins University, 1881 (Box 34)
    - Typothetae of New York –Dinner, 1886 (Box 34)
    - American Copyright League Dinner, 1888 (Box 34)
    - Sidney Lanier Memorial, Johns Hopkins University, 1888 (Box 34)
    - U.S. Senate. Committee on patents re. copyright bill, 1888 (Box 34)
    - American Copyright League Dinner, 1891 (Box 34)
    - Whittier funeral, 1892 (Box 34)
    - Esther Carpenter Memorial, 1894 (Box 34)
    - O.B. Frothingham Memorial, 1895 (Box 34)
    - R.L. Stevenson Memorial Meeting, 1895 (Box 34)
    - Authors' Club Dinner for R.H. Stoddard, 1897 (Box 34)
    - Tolstoy Dinner, 1898 (Box 34)
    - Watchnight at the Players for Edwin Booth, 1898 (Box 34)
    - Presentation of Whitelaw Reid's portrait, 1899 (Box 34)
    - Authors Club, 1900 (Box 34)
    - New York Stock Exchange, 1900 (Box 34)
    - Norwich, Ct., Arbor Day, 1900 (Box 34)
    - Press Club, 1900 (Box 34)
    - Author's Club reception for Seth Low, 1901 (Box 34)
    - Hoi Scholastkoi Dinner, 1901 (Box 34)
    - St. Lawrence Univ. Dinner for Irving Bacheller, 1901 (Box 34)
    - University Club Dinner for Hamilton W. Mabie, 1901 (Box 34)
    - The Lotos Club Dinner for E.H. Abbey, 1902 (Box 34)
    - New England Society Dinner, 1902 (Box 34)
    - Army and Navy Journal Dinner for W.C. Church, 1903 (Box 34)
    - Church Reception for Robert Collyer, 1903 (Box 34)
    - Funeral of R.H. Stoddard, 1903 (Box 34)
    - New England Society Dinner, 1903 (Box 34)
    - Author’s Club, for F.R. Stockton, 1904 (Box 34)
    - Carnegie Dinner for John Morley, 1904 (Box 34)
    - Testimonial to Mme Mojeska, 1905 (Box 34)
    - Norwich Board of Trade Dinner, 1906 (Box 34)
    - Keats-Shelley Entertainment, 1907 (Box 34)
  - The star bearer (Box 34)
  - Stoddard, Richard Henry (Box 34)
  - Stoddard's last poem (Box 34)
  - The sulphur gatherers (Box 34)
  - Swedenborg (Box 34)
  - Tenyson (Box 35)
  - Terra ab astris (Box 35)
  - The test (Box 35)
  - Theocritus (Box 35)
  - Thomas Bailey Aldrich (Box 35)
  - [Thompson] (Box 35)
  - Times are harder…(poem to E.B.D. Stoddard) (Box 35)
  - To A.R. Macdonough (Box 35)
  - To Austin Dobson (Box 35)
  - To C.O.B. [Cyrus Osborne Baker] (Box 35)
  - To Dr. John Williamson Palmer (Box 35)
  - To Dr. Waldstein… (Box 35)
  - To E.[Eugene Field] (Box 35)
  - To Howard (Box 35)
  - To joy (Box 35)
  - To L.H.S. [Mrs Stedman] (Box 35)
  - To Lucy Catlin Bull [Mrs Robinson] (Box 35)
  - To Louise (Box 35)
  - To Thomas D. English (Box 35)
  - To William Sharp (Box 35)
  - Toasts (Box 35)
  - Too late! (Box 35)
  - A town sermon (Box 35)
  - Treasure tombs at Mycenae (Box 35)
  - The tree-planter (Box 35)
  - Truffles (Box 35)
  - Twelve years of British song (Box 35)
  - The twins (Box 35)
  - "Ubi sunt qui ante nos?" (Box 35)
  - A Victorian anthology (Box 35)
  - Victorian poets (Box 35)
  - View of neurasthenia (Box 35)
  - A vigil (Box 35)
  - Voice of the western wind (Box 35)
  - The voyage of life (Box 35)
  - Wanted--a man (Box 36)
  - Westminster Abbey (Box 36)
  - What is criticism? (Box 36)
  - White frost (Box 36)
  - Whitman, Walt (Box 36)
  - Whittier (Box 36)
  - Whittier, John Greenleaf (Encyclopedia Britanica) (Box 36)
  - The Whittier Home Association (Box 36)
  - William Watson (Box 36)
  - A wish (Box 36)
  - With a book, to Robin MacKaye (Box 36)
  - With De Quincey's Opium Eater to Sanford B. Hunt (Box 36)
  - With Hancock at Williamsburg (Box 36)
  - The works of Edgar Allan Poe (Box 36)
  - "The World" directory [annotated by Stedman] (Box 36)
  - The world well lost (Box 36)
  - Written for the Authors' Album given to Mrs. Cleveland (Box 36)
  - Yale ode tor Commencement Day (Box 36)
  - The Yankee (Box 36)
  - Ye tombe of ye poet Chaucer (Box 36)
  - Unidentified and misc. fragments (Box 36)
- Series V: Scrapbooks
  - #1 & #2: War Correspondence, (2 volumes) (Box 37)
  - #3: Mater Coronata Reviews (Box 37)
  - #4: Addresses and Occasions (Box 599)
  - #5: [Poems Now First Collected] (Reviews, etc.) (Box 38)
  - #6: New Poe Edition/National Institute/Keats-Shelley Fune, 1907 (Box 38)
  - #7: Victorian Anthology--Reviews and Press Notices (Box 39)
  - #8: The Nature and Elements of Poetry (Box 39)
  - #9: Personal Addresses and Occasions/Notices and reviews of the Pocket Guide/History of the Stock Exchange (Box 39)
  - #10: Victorian Poets (13th Edition) (Box 39)
  - #11: [Miscellaneous—news] (Box 39)
  - #12: Miscellaneous Reviews/Occasions (Box 40)
  - #13: E.C.S. Articles (Box 40)
  - #14 & #15: An American Anthology. Press Notices and Reviews Voloumes I & II (Box 40)
  - #16: Appeal for Letters—Review of Poems.Swinburne Letters and reviews/Life and Letters (Box 40)
  - #17: Personal (Box 41)
  - #18: Poets of America (Box 41)
  - #19: Death Notices of E.C. Stedman/Tributes and articles called forth by the death of E.C. Stedman/Memorial Meeting, 1907/Death Notice of Arthur Stedman (Box 41)
  - #20: "Kelp Rock"—guest book (some entries analyzed) (Box 41)
  - #21: Walt Whitman (Box 41)
- Series VI: Financial and Genealogical Material
  - Financial papers (Box 42)
  - Genealogical manuscripts (Box 43)
- Series VII: Laura Stedman Gould
  - Manuscripts and notes (3 Boxes) (Box 44-46)
- Series VIII: Printed Materials
  - Printed materials (11 Boxes) (Box 47-57)
- Series IX: Photographs
  - (4 Boxes) (Box 58-61)
  - Original photographs (Box 595)
  - Portrait of Andrew Jackson (plate) (Box 595)
  - Photographs – Miscellaneous groups (Box 596)
  - Photographs – E.C. Stedman (Box 596)
  - Photographs – Stedman Home: "Casa Hausa" Bronxville, NY (Box 596)
  - Miscellaneous photograph: Shelly’s tomb or monument (Box 596)
  - Photograph: Stedman hime, "Kelp Rock" New Castle, NH (Box 596)
  - Bas-relief (Box 597)
- Series X: Library of American Literature
  - Bound volumes (Box 62-77)
  - Quotes and Revisions (Box 78)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence and documents (Box 79)
  - Portraits (engravings) (Box 80-81)
  - Portraits (engravings) (Box 82)
  - Original photographs for L. A. L. (Box 82)
  - Portrait scrolls (engravings)_ (Box 83)
  - Portraits (plates) (Box 83)
  - Portraits (plates) (Box 84-85)
- Series XI: Edward M. Williams
  - "The Contructive Art" The criticism of Stedman (manuscropts and notecards) (2 Boxes) (Box 86-87)